120 YEARS AGO…
（120年前）
Saki…!
早紀小姐
-Answer me, Saki! -Saki…!
-回答啊 -早紀小姐
-Did you find her? -Over here…!
-有找到她嗎？ -找到了
-Is that Saki? -There she is!
-是早紀小姐嗎？
-It's Saki! -Here she is.
-是早紀小姐 -找到了
Saki!
早紀
Can you confirm that this is your sister?
確實是你妹妹沒錯嗎？
Was she… killed?
我妹妹是被殺害的嗎？
I don't know.
我也不知道
Wake up.
-快醒醒 -快醒醒啊
Hey, wake up.
快醒來啦
-Tsugumi? -Are you all right?
-津輕小姐 -快起來
She woke up.
醒了
Good morning.
早安
-Are you all right? -Water.
-還好吧？ -水，來…
Drink some water.
-來，津輕小姐 -喝點水
Good.
很好…
Are you all right?
小心，還好嗎？
Oops, this is sake.
怪了，這根本是酒啊
HARUKA TSUGARU
（津輕晴果）
TSUGUMI
（繼實）
Hello?
你好
Help me.
姊姊，救救我
What happened?
怎麼了？
I went out for drinking with medical students,
我跟醫學系學生喝酒
but they set me up.
-但我被騙了 -快開門，津輕小姐
Are you all right, Tsugumi?
津輕小姐，你沒事吧？
-They are not medical students. -Hey! Hey!
-喂 -這些傢伙絕對不是醫學系學生
Why did you go out with such people?
笨蛋，怎麼跑去那種地方啊？
-Because I thought -Are you okay? Did you get it up?
-我想或許能打聽到 -沒事吧？有起來嗎？
-I could pick up some information. -Hey, open up, Tsugumi.
-新的情報啊 -快開門啊，津輕小姐
-What should I do? -Tsugumi!
-怎麼辦，姊姊？ -津輕小姐
I think they're going to take me somewhere.
我好像會被他們強行帶走啊
Run away.
什麼？快點逃啊
Don't cry, yell, or get upset.
聽好了，別大哭大喊，不能太激動
It's bad for your cerebral vessels if you suffer an attack.
要是發作了，對你頭部血管不好
Do you understand?
知道了嗎？總之
Find someone. I'll go there right away.
逃到人多的地方，我馬上去找你
-She is running away! -Wait!
-逃走了… -給我等等！
TSUGUMI
（繼實）
We got you.
好，抓到了
Don't run away from us.
怎麼能亂逃呢？
TSUGUMI
（繼實）
Aren't we going to your apartment?
怪了，不是要去你的公寓嗎？
My family's summer house is up here.
我家的別墅在這上面
We can have a party there.
那裡不管鬧到多大聲都行
Don't go home yet.
真的是，津輕小姐怎麼能先逃呢？
Help me!
救救我！
You've got to be kidding me.
你一定是在開玩笑
He should be fine. Let's go.
應該沒事的，快走吧
What if he is still alive?
要是她還活著怎麼辦？
Are you going to ruin our lives?
你要害我的人生完蛋嗎？
-Right? -Stop it.
-是嗎？ -別吵了啦
You should have driven more carefully.
誰叫你沒看好
Don't blame me!
-才不是我的錯 -滾開
-Hey! -This is your fault.
-給我等等 -都是你的錯
She's running!
她跑了！
Don't let her go.
-混帳東西，不會讓你逃走的！ -喂！
-Wait! -Stop!
-給我站住！ -等等！
Don't even think that you can run away from us.
你以為逃得了嗎？
-You have a lot of nerve. -Hey…
-膽子還真大啊 -以為逃得了嗎？
Who are you?
你是誰？
We must get him.
這傢伙很不妙啊
Eat this!
快上啊
Tsugumi!
繼實
Haruka.
姊姊
-Tsugumi. -What happened?
-繼實 -怎麼了？
Where am I?
這裡是哪裡？
That's what I wanted to ask you. Where have you been?
我才想問呢，你跑去哪裡了？
They put me in a car.
我被強拉上車
What?
什麼？
I run away from them and went into the forest.
逃到森林裡…
Tsugumi.
繼實
Let's go to the police and the hospital. I'll come with you.
姊姊也會陪著你的 我們去醫院，然後報警吧
Okay, Tsugumi?
好嗎？繼實
No, they didn't do anything to me.
不是啦，我沒被怎麼樣
What?
什麼？
Nothing happened, and I didn't see anything.
我沒被怎麼樣，大概也什麼都沒看到
What are you talking about?
你胡說什麼啊？
I'm fine.
我沒事的
Take some medicine.
好了，快吃藥
What is it?
什麼？
There it is.
真是的
I want that paper back. That's not fair.
把那時用的紙還來，卑鄙小人
You have been working hard with her
那是我和老闆娘兩人拼命工作…
-Good morning. -and saving money.
-早安 -好不容易存了錢
Now you became a great landlord.
才能有現在的地位
-Is this an experiment? -To the both of you.
-這是實驗嗎？ -你們兩個
Congratulations anyway.
還說什麼“恭喜”
What are you talking about?
到底在胡說什麼？
That's the end of the story.
本人深感惶恐
This was Daiku-shirabe.
以上就是大木作調查的故事
DAIKO SHIRABE MIYAJI KEI
（大木作調查，落語家桂宮治）
-Okay. Check it out. -Okay.
-好，測試吧 -是
How was it?
怎麼樣？
My blood sugar went down.
我的順利下降了呢
Although I ate pancake for breakfast this morning,
早餐時，我雖然吃了鬆餅
my blood sugar level didn't increase.
但血糖上升被抑制了
My blood sugar level has increased.
我則是上升了
Is this because of stress?
會因為壓力導致血糖上升嗎？
Do you feel stressed when you listen to Rakugo?
你聽落語會覺得有壓力啊？
I think you picked up the wrong one. That was a story about a carpenter.
是教授您選的主題不太巧 選這個大木作調查
My father is also a carpenter.
我爸就是木匠
I felt stressed because this story reminded me of my father.
讓我想到我父親，所以感受到壓力
I see. But that's too ordinary.
原來如此，但這樣未免太理所當然了
"Stress is bad for health. Smile."
有壓力不好，要健康就多笑
That's not even a scientific fact.
這已經是足以稱為科學的事實了
What I want to know is
進一步說，我想知道的是
whether the excellent art of speech has a good influence on the human body
優秀的談話藝術，優秀的藝文活動 先不管個人的狀況
regardless of personal reasons.
是否能為身體帶來好的影響
In other words,
舉例來說
can the theatre play of Chekhov or Shakespeare
看了莎士比亞或契訶夫的戲劇
activate the power of DNA that has been sleeping
沉眠已久的遺傳基因力 是否能被打開
and make a positive impact on the cell?
為細胞帶來好的影響呢？
If not, is it because of the performers or the story?
若沒辦法的話
Do you think DNA can work like an art critic?
遺傳基因有這種劇評家的功用嗎？
Let's try Kokontei Shinsho next.
那接著試試看古今亭志生吧
Let's have a break.
不，先休息一下吧
People get bored if they keep doing the same thing.
繼續下去會覺得無聊的
Boredom is the "enemy" of stress. I mean, "friend".
無聊是壓力的敵人
You are right.
是啊
Dr. Tsurumaru, please take a look at this.
那麼鶴丸先生，請您看看這個
Is this a mushroom?
-什麼，是蘑菇啊？ -是的
Yes. Please take a closer look.
但請您再仔細看看
Isn't this the Akanarikamitake mushroom?
這是赤成君菇，不是嗎？
It's rare. Is this artificially grown?
現在這很稀奇呢，是哪裡種的？
No. I think it's natural.
不是，我想應該是天然的
It looks different.
應該不是吧
The Akanarikamitake mushroom is orange.
赤成君菇應該更偏橘色吧
This is red.
這太紅了吧
Have you ever seen a live Akanarikamitake mushroom?
你有看過真正的赤成君菇嗎？
No. But the natural one wouldn't grow around here.
沒有，但是天然的 不可能在這附近找到
I know. That's why I'm curious.
所以才更不可思議啊
Did you find it near here?
你在這附近採的嗎？
I think it's somewhere around here.
應該…就在這附近…
Don't you know where it was found?
你不知道在哪裡？
No.
我不知道
Broadleaf and coniferous trees near here are cultivated artificially.
但這附近的山雖都是闊葉林
The Akanarikamitake mushroom can grow only in the primeval forest of conifer.
只會生長在原生針葉林的赤成君菇
So…
所以呢？
So even if this is not an Akanarikamitake mushroom,
所以就算不是赤成君菇
a similar new mushroom can grow in the forest near here.
還是可以推測相近的新菌類 就長在這附近的森林
If you can prove that it is not an Akanarikamitake mushroom,
若能證明這不是赤成君菇
it's a newly-discovered species of mushroom.
就代表我們發現了新品種的菇
Exactly.
沒錯
There you go. That's why you are a "fungi girl".
真不愧是菌類女子，菌女
Don't call me that. It's like bullying back in school.
請住口，對小學生是霸凌了
Where will you go look?
那要去哪裡找呢？
That's the problem.
這就是問題了
I don't know where this is found.
我就是不知道自己 是在哪裡找到這個的
Huh?
什麼？
Finding a new mushroom in the forest is like grabbing onto a cloud.
要在森林裡尋找不知名的菇類 就跟要抓住雲朵一樣
…they are cram school students.
被發現時
They were semiconscious, laying
已經躺在地上
on the ground when they were found.
意識不清了
Please turn on the TV again.
等等，看一下電視，快把電視打開
Hurry…
快點…
… because they got a rash,
從皮膚表面出現異變可推測
it is considered that they went into the forest
他們帶著半玩樂心態 踏入了森林，觸摸到某種菌類
and touched some kind of fungi that causes an allergy…
引發了過敏症狀
What's wrong?
-怎麼了？ -在這些區域發現的樹…
-Are you sick? -I'm fine.
-身體不舒服嗎？ -我沒事
Do you know the students who were on TV?
該不會
No.
不是
-I can help you. -With what?
-有煩惱的話我來幫忙吧 -幫什麼？
-Finding the mushroom. -No, thanks.
-尋找菌菇 -沒問題的
Let me help you. You need a car to go to a mountain.
讓我幫忙吧 那在深山裡吧？沒車很麻煩的
I am good at mountain climbing.
我很習慣爬山了
But you don't know which mountain you should go.
但你不知道在哪座山吧？
I have an idea.
不，我大概知道了
Like what?
你怎麼知道的？
Don't worry. I can find it by myself.
沒問題的 我一個人就能找，讓我找吧
Just as you'd expect from "fungi girl".
真不愧是菌女
Don't call me that.
別這樣叫我
Don't push yourself too hard. You can count on me.
但你不用逞強，儘管依靠我吧
I don't like people who don't try hard.
我雖然討厭不努力的人
But I can't just leave people who are pushing themselves too hard.
但我無法放著逞強的人不管
-Inaniwa. -Yes?
-稻庭學長 -什麼？
Some people don't count on you.
並不是不依靠你的人
It doesn't mean they're pushing themselves too hard.
都是逞強的人
I just wanted to let you know. Bye.
我提醒你一下而已，失陪了
I think she is pushing herself too hard.
總覺得還是有點逞強啊
Who's there?
誰？
Who are you?
你是誰？
Huh?
什麼？
Why are you here?
為何會在這裡？
Why?
為什麼？
Did you survive?
你還活著嗎？
-Didn't you die… 120 years ago? -Excuse me.
你還沒死嗎？
I won't do anything.
我什麼都不會做
I'm just here.
我只是待在這裡而已
I…
我…
I am not human.
不是人類
Please forget that you saw me.
請你忘了在這裡遇見我的事
Ouch…
好痛…
It hurts.
好痛
Why are you following me?
為何要跟著我？
I am a scientist.
我是科學家
I am still a student.
雖然我還是學生
So, I am an aspiring scientist.
只能說是菜鳥預備軍
That's why I can't believe what you are saying.
所以，我沒辦法相信你說的話
I can't forget about you
我無法忘記你的存在
because I saw you.
只要我親眼看到了就不行
Do you really not know me?
你真的不認識我嗎？
No.
不認識
So, I want to know about you.
所以，我想了解你的事情
I want to know what I don't know.
我想了解不了解的事
I don't want to die without knowing what I want to know.
我不想在不了解的情況下死掉
I envy you.
真令人羨慕
Huh?
什麼？
Please don't follow me anymore.
別再…跟著我了
What's that?
那是？
That's my house.
我的家
May I come visit?
我能去打擾嗎？
Wow. There is electricity.
真厲害，原來這裡有電啊
Thank you for having me.
打擾了
Do you really live here?
你真的在這裡生活嗎？
-Do you live alone? -Yes. I'm alone now.
-一個人生活？ -現在是一個人
Were there anyone else before?
之前有別人在嗎？
My dad.
之前我父親還在
I've seen a TV drama Kitano Kunikara.
你有看過重播的連續劇 《來自北國》嗎？
Is that similar to your situation?
是像那樣嗎？
I don't know what you are saying.
我不懂你在說什麼
You don't know that drama?
你沒看過嗎？
You don't like watching TV?
你是家裡不放電視的那種人嗎？
I have never watched TV.
我沒看過電視
Never?
沒看過？
When did you start living here?
你從何時開始住在這裡的？
Hundred and twenty years ago.
120年前
Don't be silly. Please answer my question.
別開玩笑了，認真回答我
What do you do for a living?
你靠什麼維生呢？
What do you eat?
你都吃什麼過活呢？
Mushrooms!
菌菇？
Are they edible?
這可以吃嗎？
Can I have one?
-那個… -能拿一個嗎？
I don't know if it's safe for humans.
我不知道人類能不能吃
I'll check.
我只是想調查一下
Please don't be silly.
別說些奇怪的話，好嗎？
Who are you?
你到底是誰？
What did you do before you came here?
來這裡之前都在做什麼？
I can keep any kind of secret.
無論是什麼秘密，我都能保守
Even if you are… a criminal.
就算你是犯罪者也一樣
I won't tell anyone about you.
我不會告訴任何人關於你的事
I promise.
我發誓
Aren't you afraid of me?
你不怕我嗎？
Afraid?
怕？
No. I'm not afraid of you.
我不怕
As I said, I don't want to die without knowing what I want to know.
我不是說過了嗎？
I'm not afraid of common sense.
我不害怕常識
What I'm afraid of is knowing nothing.
我只害怕自己一無所知
Knowing nothing?
一無所知？
Please tell me about yourself.
請告訴我關於你的事
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
I was born from my father.
我…是父親生下來的
From your father?
父親生的？
What about your mother?
令堂呢？
I have no mother.
我沒有母親
My father was a doctor of medicine.
我父親是醫學博士
I… I was dead.
我…已經死了
My father raised me from the dead.
是父親讓我死而復生的
Please don't be silly.
別開玩笑了
It… It sounds like you are Frankenstein.
這種事…根本是科學怪人啊
I'm sorry.
抱歉
My father's room is downstairs.
父親的房間在樓下
I am not being silly.
我沒騙你
He is my father.
這是我的父親
I was born in here 120 years ago.
120年前，我是在這裡出生的
-In here? -Yes.
-在這裡？ -對
"Kentaro Fukashi."
“深志研太郎”
That is the name of my father.
那是家父的名字
What is your name?
你的名字呢？
Name?
沒人
He didn't give me a name.
幫我取名字
I am not human.
因為我不是人類
So, I will be here forever.
所以我一直待在這裡
First, my father taught me about humans.
關於人類的事 大部分都是家父教我的
After he died, I learned from a radio I found.
家父過世後 我撿到了收音機，繼續學習
But…
但是
I can't live with humans.
我無法跟人類生活
You look nothing but a human.
你怎麼看都是人類
Don't you feel lonely to be here all by yourself?
你不寂寞嗎？ 一直都孤獨一人待在這種地方
I am like this forest.
我就和這座森林一樣
My father told me to live like the forest.
父親要我像是森林一樣地活著
But you want to know about humans, don't you?
但是，你想了解人類，對吧？
-Hello. -You look so well.
-吐舌頭 -你還真有精神啊
You can't pronounce it clearly though.
雖然感覺有點說慣了
It's almost 3 p.m. Let's call SNACK MAN.
但馬上就要三點了，來呼叫點心男吧
Where is he today?
今天在哪裡呢？
It's time for you and I
你和我的時間
Evolutionary theory for you and I
我和你的進化論
Ask Amakusa if you are
有煩惱就問天草
Worried about something
去問問天草吧
Hello. I am Junpei Amakusa.
好的，我是天草純平
Who wants my advice today?
今天收到了這樣的煩惱
It's from Karashirenkon from Kumamoto.
熊本縣辣蓮藕先生，35歲
He is a 35-year-old high school teacher.
職業是高中老師
A female student said that she wanted to go out with me.
前幾天被某個高中女生告白了
She is very attractive…
雖然她非常有魅力…
You can go back to town from here.
從這裡走下去就不會迷路了
Please go.
請離開吧
Don't you ever come down from the mountain?
你不打算下山嗎？
I have several times in the night.
我在深夜裡下山過幾次
You want to see people, don't you?
其實你很想見見人類吧？
I understand that you are afraid of seeing people,
雖然我也不是不能理解 你怕看到人類的心情
but you will get used to them.
這種事我早就習慣了
You are the one who suffers by having a narrow view of the world.
讓自己活在小世界裡 最後痛苦的也是自己
You have no problem talking to people.
你也能跟人溝通
Let's go.
走吧
You will be fine. I'm with you.
我會陪你的，沒問題的吧
Right? Let's go.
好嗎？一起走吧
MIKUTAKE
（美久岳公車站）
I haven't gone beyond here.
我沒去過比這裡更遠的地方
You must be the one who saved me.
是你救了我吧？
Right?
對吧？
It's a bicycle.
腳踏車
It's an electric bicycle.
電動腳踏車
Electric…?
電動？
Would you like to try?
要騎騎看嗎？
I have never tried to ride a bicycle before.
我沒騎過腳踏車
You can change your past experience.
只要用這個穿越結界就好了呀
Here you go.
來吧
Put your feet here.
把腳放在這裡
Push the pedals using your feet and move forward.
用腳交互踩踏，慢慢往前進
Good.
沒錯
That's good. See?
沒錯…對，看吧？
Hey! Do you know how to apply the brakes?
等等，剎車，知道怎麼踩剎車嗎？
Hey!
嘿！
Put on the brakes!
剎車啊！
Are you all right?
天啊，你沒事吧？
I'm fine.
我沒事
How could you be all right?
這樣怎麼會沒事？
"Tsugaru…"
津輕？
I haven't introduced myself yet.
這麼說來 我還沒跟你說過我的名字吧？
My name is Tsugumi Tsugaru.
我叫做津輕繼實
Please wait here.
請等我一下
Tsugaru…
津輕
Tsugumi.
繼實
I'm home.
我回來了
Haruka?
姊姊？
It's okay. Please come in.
沒問題，請進吧
Yes.
是
Please take off your shoes.
那個…鞋子，請把鞋子脫掉
Here you are.
來
First, please take a bath before my sister comes home.
首先，在我姐回來之前 請你趕快洗個澡吧
Bath?
洗澡？
Maybe you don't realize that,
或許你自己沒注意到
but you have a wild smell.
但你有一股野味
Soil. Tree.
是土還是木頭呢？
You smell like a mushroom.
有一股菌菇的香氣
Maybe because you eat a lot of mushrooms.
或許是因為你總是吃菌菇
I am used to its smell,
我已經很習慣了
but my sister is a nurse and she is sensitive to smell and dirt.
但我姊是護士 對髒汙或氣味很敏感的
A bath.
洗澡
Taking a bath is to soak in hot water.
洗澡就是指泡進熱水裡
Like this.
就像這樣，噗通
How should I explain him to Haruka?
該怎麼跟姊姊解釋呢？
A homeless person?
流浪漢？
Are you done?
好了嗎？
Do you feel dizzy or something?
你應該沒泡過頭吧？沒事吧？
No. I'm fine.
-我沒事 -那個…
Please get out before my sister comes home.
在我姊回來之前，你能出來就好了
Okay.
好
I'm out.
我出來了
Please put on your clothes!
衣服…快把衣服穿上！
I… I saw it.
這是怎麼回事？不小心看到了
Now he looks nothing but human.
越來越覺得他是人類了啊
Please wear this.
請換上這個
I like your jacket, but it stands out.
雖然你的衣服很棒，但有點太顯眼了
Let's pretend that you are my senior at university.
就說你是我的學長好了
I have many strange seniors.
反正學長裡本來就很多怪人
Here you go.
來吧，請換上
Good. Let me clear the tub.
很適合你呢，那我去放熱水囉
An Akanarikamitake mushroom?
是剛摘下來的赤成君菇
Why?
怎麼會？
Oh no.
不好了
Oh.
快來
-When I say go, -I'm home.
-我叫你衝的時候… -我回來了
get out of the house.
你就從這裡出去，離開這個家
-Out? -Leave the house. Okay?
-外面？ -到家外面等我一下，懂嗎？
-Okay.
-是 -說好囉
Hi, Haruka. I took a bath.
姊姊，歡迎回來，我剛才在洗澡
Don't you think it's stinky here?
不覺得家裡臭臭的嗎？
I went to the mountain from the university today.
我今天去爬了大學那邊的山
Let me get some fresh air.
換氣…通通風
Did you really take a bath?
你真的洗過澡了嗎？
You smell like the forest.
總覺得全身草腥味啊
Go!
衝啊
-Huh? -Go!
-什麼？ -衝啊！
What are you talking about?
你到底在胡說什麼啊？
Go!
衝啊！
Tsugumi, are you all right?
什麼？怎麼了？
What's wrong with you?
哪裡痛嗎，繼實？
I said go!
叫你快衝啊
Wait a minute.
等等
What is it?
等等！
What was that?
剛才那是怎麼回事？
-A thief, maybe. -A thief?
-應該是小偷吧 -小偷？
Now that he's gone, it's okay.
沒問題，已經跑掉了
I have to go back to the university.
-姊姊，我要回大學一趟了 -什麼？
-I'm sorry. -Hey, Tsugumi!
-很抱歉！ -繼…繼實？
Good morning.
早安
Did you stay in the lab last night?
你昨晚睡在研究室啊？
What's this?
這是什麼？
It's awesome.
也太厲害了吧
Where did you find this?
你到底是在哪找到的？
I… I don't know.
不，我也不知道
What do you mean?
什麼叫不知道啊？
You don't have to hide it from me.
不用對我隱瞞啊
Wait!
等等！
Who is he? Do you know him?
-等等！ -那是誰？你認識？
I met him in the mountain.
是我在山上認識的
Why is he in my locker?
他為何躲在那種地方？
He is shy.
因為他很怕生
I see.
這樣啊
I'm Seiya Inaniwa, a graduate student.
我是研究生稻庭聖哉
He is eccentric.
還真嚴重啊
Please step back first.
總之我們先從這裡
Sure.
-離開一下吧 -對喔
Good morning.
-早安
Who is he?
那是誰？
Is this okay?
這樣好嗎？
I need to talk to you.
我跟各位商量一下
What is it?
怎麼了？
He is strange.
那個人很奇怪
-Sure he is. -Please listen.
-當然奇怪 -請安靜聽我說
-Okay. -Why is he strange?
-好 -怎樣奇怪？
He said that he is not a human.
他說他不是人類
He has been living in the deep forest.
他好像一直住在深山的森林裡
He said that he lived there for 120 years.
他說他從120年前開始就住在那了
Do you think he is out of his mind?
也就是說他腦袋壞掉了？
But many strange things happened.
但發生了許多不可思議的事
I'm not sure if he is human or not.
所以我也不太清楚 他到底是不是人類
Do you think that he is not human?
你想說他真的不是人嗎？
He said that he is Frankenstein.
他是這樣說的，他說自己是科學怪人
To be more precise, he is something similar to Frankenstein.
正確來說，是有點像科學怪人之類的
Actually, Frankenstein is a doctor who made Frankenstein.
原作的正確名稱不是《科學怪人》 而是《創造怪人的博士》
Then he is a monster.
-那也一樣是怪人！ -是
His father was a doctor of medicine and raised him from the dead.
他稱之為父親的醫學博士 讓他死而復生
Is he a mythomaniac?
這是說謊成性嗎？
Do you want me to check if what he says is true?
所以是想要我看看這是否屬實？
Yes.
沒錯
I have no one to ask but you.
我只能拜託老師了
All right.
我明白了
Are you sure?
老師，您當真嗎？
Yes, of course.
當然
If you think things that can't be proven scientifically won't happen,
認為科學無法證明的事就不會發生
it's blasphemy against science.
反而是褻瀆科學
-Well said! -Which side are you on?
-就是該這樣 -你到底想怎樣？
Curiosity is the first step to research.
好奇是研究的第一步
His father didn't give him a name and raised him in the forest.
總之他稱為父親的人
I saw a skeleton of his father.
他說是父親的人 也確實化成了白骨在現場
Maybe I should report it to the police.
所以或許應該要報案才對
Is there any possibility that he will hurt humans?
他不會危害人類嗎？
No. Please don't worry about it.
這倒是沒問題
He wants to be a human. He listens to the radio.
他很憧憬人類，一直在聽廣播
Radio?
廣播？
Time for you and I
你和我的時間
Evolutionary theory for you and I
我和你的進化論
Ask Amakusa if you are
有煩惱就問天草
Worrying about something
去問問天草吧
The radio was the only way for him to learn about humans.
收音機是他唯一能了解人類的方式
How is your curry and rice?
咖哩飯怎麼樣？
It's delicious.
非常美味
It's nice to see him act normally.
總覺得放心多了 看到了他普通的反應
I know.
就是說啊
I can't stop eating.
我停不下來
What are you going to do?
你接著要怎麼做？
Are you going back to the forest?
要回森林裡嗎？
What do you want? Do you want to stay here?
怎麼樣？還想待著嗎？
How about my house?
要來我家嗎？
Many people come and stay at my house.
我家常常有人來住
I have extra rooms.
也有空房間
It may be a good place for him to go back to society.
很適合回歸社會的時期呢
Your family runs an office of…
我記得你家是…
Building contractors.
建築公司
-You mean a carpenter? -Yes.
-建築木工？ -嗯
I think he is cut out for it.
或許很適合呢
-You are right. -That's good.
-是啊 -還真辛苦呢
Yes.
感覺很不錯
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
DAILY LUNCH SPECIALS
（每日午餐）
-Do you like that pop singer? -Pop singer?
-你喜歡那個偶像啊？ -偶像？
Her name is Ririe Ohmiya, who used to belong to an idol group.
那個叫大宮莉莉惠的 不就是之前待在某團體的？
He may be a man…
果然是個男人啊
Amakusa.
天草
I see. It's Amakusa.
不是啦，是天草
Ask Amakusa
去問問天草吧
Amakusa?
天草？
Amakusa.
天草
Do you want me to ask if you can keep that poster?
去幫你問能否拿這張海報吧？
What's next?
這次又怎麼了？
Do you want it?
你想要嗎？
Excuse me.
-不好意思 -是
-I want to buy this. -Welcome!
-我要買這個 -歡迎，好的
-It's 100 yen. Thank you. -Okay.
-這樣是一百元，謝謝 -來
This mushroom is artificially cultivated.
這是人工栽培的菌菇
Artificially cultivated?
人工栽培？
This is Shimeji, which is artificially cultivated by humans.
這是人類栽種的菌菇，鴻喜菇
-Do humans cultivate mushrooms? -We love mushrooms.
-人也會栽種菌菇嗎？ -大家都很喜歡呢
It's raw.
雖然是生的
It's tasty.
好吃
I like mushroom cultivated by humans.
人類栽種的菌菇很美味
You do like mushrooms.
你真的很喜歡菌菇呢
Let's go.
好，走吧
INANIWA CORPORATION
（稻庭建築公司）
Drink later.
晚點再喝吧
Shut up.
混帳東西
You can't see the true character of people without drinking.
不喝酒哪能看出人的本性？
You just drink and reveal your own character.
你只會暴露自己的本性吧
So, when can you start working here?
然後呢？何時能來上班？
Can he stay here?
他已經被錄取了？
He will stay here starting tonight.
就說了從今天開始啊
I said he had no place to go.
-不是說沒地方住嗎？ -很好
I have nothing to say if he prepares for what's ahead.
既然你都做好這種覺悟了 我也不囉嗦了
He is not ready, but he has a reason.
哪有什麼覺悟？只是有些事
What's your name?
你叫什麼名字？
Hey! I'm asking your name.
喂，我在問你名字啊
"Kentaro Fukashi."
“深志研太郎”
Fukashi.
他叫
Ken.
深志研
Ken? Is that the same as Ken Takakura?
是健先生嗎？高倉健的健？
No. Ken is for "the lab".
不，是研究的研
The "lab"? Not "fist" nor "modesty"?
研究的研？不是拳頭的拳 也不是謙虛的謙？而是研？
That's the lowest status among all kinds of kanji.
這在這發音的名字裡 是排行最低的啊
I don't know what he is saying.
你知道他在說什麼嗎？
Don't worry, he doesn't make sense most of the time.
他平時說的話就沒什麼意義 別放在心上
-Excuse me. -How are you?
-大家好 -打擾了
She is Tamara. She used to be a live-in worker.
這位是玉名小姐 她以前也借住在這裡
Now she got married and works as a housekeeper.
現在已經結婚了 每天通勤幫我們公司處理雜物跟家務
And she is taking care of our boss.
社長那方面的需求也是她處理唷
That's your current job.
那現在是你的工作吧
No, it's not.
才沒有咧
Don't look at me like that.
不准你這樣看我
She is Murozono. She is a live-in craftsman.
她是寄住在這裡的工匠，室園小姐
Call me Mikoto. I broke ties with my family.
叫我美琴，我已經跟家人斷絕關係了
She is the only person who lives here other than my family.
現在只有她一人住在這裡
Don't ignore me.
別無視我啊
Mikoto is my disciple. She can do everything now.
美琴是我一手拉拔的，已經很厲害了
Call me Murozono. They may think that I'm your girlfriend.
叫我室園，人家會懷疑我們的關係的
Many women work here.
這裡好像很多女性呢
He likes women after my mother died.
是他的興趣 自從老媽過世後就是這樣
He picks up girls in town, takes them to karaoke,
在街上跟我搭訕，去唱歌後
teaches them lessons, and brings them home.
就一直說教，帶我來這裡
I can't ignore women who are stubborn.
看到逞強地活著的傢伙 我就無法置之不理啊
Don't touch me.
別碰我
You use runaway girls at a low wage.
根本只是利用離家出走的少女 用便宜工資叫我工作
He is called a night patrol.
這叫做夜間援助面試
Most of them leave soon.
一般人都會逃出去
It's rare to see someone who stays here as long as you.
像你這樣一直待著的很少
Don't be rude.
你這樣說太失禮囉
Don't worry about that.
-這傢伙無所謂 -這樣啊
Who are you?
你又是誰？
She is Tsugaru, my junior at University.
她是我的學妹，津輕小姐
She is a "fungi girl".
她是“菌女”
What is that?
住附近又怎樣？
Don't use a nickname that requires explanation.
別總是用那種難以說明的方式叫我啊
You are right.
也對
Mikoto. He is your junior from today. Take good care of him.
好，美琴 今天起他是晚輩，你要多照顧他
Call me Murozono.
就說叫我室園了
I am not his girlfriend.
我跟社長完全沒關係
I'll knock you out if you doubt that I could be his girlfriend.
要是你讓我有這種感覺 我馬上把你揍扁
-I don't know what she is saying. -Are you a comedian?
-我不知道你在說什麼 -你是三明治人嗎？
You will get used to it.
總之彼此很快就會習慣了
Don't you need his CV?
那個，不用給你們履歷書嗎？
I don't believe in CVs.
我不相信履歷書
I only believe in every single day that you will spend here.
我相信的 只有你接下來度過的每一天
You have your CV in your future.
把你的未來當成履歷書吧 明白了嗎？
-Yes. -Just get used to his smug face.
-是 -只要習慣這張說大話
He thinks he says something cool.
得意的笑臉，就不會有其他麻煩了
It's annoying until you get used to it.
無法適應的話會很麻煩的
You can say he's annoying if you think so.
覺得麻煩時就直說吧
Okay.
我明白了
Let's eat dinner together.
總之大家一起吃飯吧
I see people, not at interviews but at dinner.
比起面試 團圓時才更能看出一個人的個性
Can I say "he is annoying" now?
“麻煩”是這時候說的嗎？
Exactly. You are a fast learner.
沒錯，你學得挺快的嘛
Try this.
要吃嗎？
Thank you.
-我開動了 -謝謝
This is your room, Ken Fukashi.
今天起這就是深志研的房間了
-Can I put it on a wall? -Sure.
-我可以貼上去嗎？ -當然
Let me bring your blanket.
我去拿棉被來
I'm sorry that I named you.
抱歉，擅自幫你取了名字
-Name? -Your name.
-名字？ -你的名字
I named you after your father.
是我從你父親的名字取的
You are Ken Fukashi from now on.
從今天起，你就是深志研
Please remember.
請記下來吧
Tsugumi Tsugaru.
津輕繼實
Yes. That's my name.
沒錯，那是我的名字
I am Tsugumi Tsugaru.
我是津輕繼實
You know me.
你認識我
I am your friend.
我是你認識的人
-Friend? -Yes.
-認識的人？ -對
Amakusa… Friend?
天草，天草是認識的人
No. He is not your friend.
那不能算是認識的人
Why?
為什麼？
I know Amakusa.
我知道天草啊
He has never seen you,
對方還沒看過你
so he is not your friend.
所以這不能算認識的人
Do you understand?
你明白了嗎？
You can't be his friend even if you keep looking at his picture.
就算你一直看他的照片 也不會變成認識的人
You can only see someone in front of you.
能夠彼此凝視的 只有和自己面對面的人
Like this.
沒錯，就像這樣
Are you having fun?
感覺很開心啊
He is my senior, Inaniwa.
這位是稻庭學長
My senior, Inaniwa.
稻庭學長
I'm not your senior.
我可不是你學長
Well, I guess I am.
是學長呢
Inaniwa is my friend.
稻庭學長是我認識的人
-That's nice to hear. -See?
-總覺得很開心呢 -對吧？
INANIWA CORPORATION
（稻庭建築公司）
Listen. You don't have to do everything from the beginning.
聽好了，一開始辦不到 也是理所當然了
I don't want to embarrass you.
這一點也不羞恥
It's important to know that you can't do anything.
知道自己什麼也辦不到是很重要的
-Am I right, boss? -Yes.
-對吧，當家？ -沒錯
What do you think you can get by knowing that you can't do anything?
雖知道什麼都辦不到 卻還能留下的是什麼？
-Room for growth. -You are annoying.
-就是成長的空間 -麻煩
What did you just say?
你說什麼？
Shishikui, he didn't mean it.
穴食先生，他不是這意思
Okay. Mikoto. You try first.
好了，美琴，你先開始做
Call me Murozono.
叫我室園
Show him your three years of experience.
讓他看看踏上這條道路 三年的實力吧
Look how thin this is.
來，快看看這有多薄
She can do this because she has been with me for three years.
這是在木頭還有我身上 花了三年培養的力量
Stop talking like we are in a relationship.
別說這種會招人誤會的話
Ouch.
好痛
Murozono, you are so good.
真不愧是室園小姐
Call me Mikoto.
叫我美琴
You are Ken Fukashi, right? It's your turn.
你叫深志研吧？你來試試
Yes.
是
You are so good.
真厲害
Is this great?
這厲害嗎？
It's not good. I've never seen such a thin shaving.
這沒失敗嗎？我沒看過這麼薄的
Idiot. He has no room for growth.
笨蛋，這樣就沒成長空間了啊
You are not a beginner, are you?
你不是外行人嗎？
Ken. How long have you been working with wood?
研先生，你跟木頭相處了多久？
Hundred and twenty years.
120年
Don't be cheeky.
別說大話了
He doesn't remember his past.
他對以前的事沒什麼印象
Did he lose his memory?
是喪失記憶了嗎？
I see. I got it.
原來如此，是這樣啊
Listen, Ken.
但是研先生
Carpenters don't learn by brain.
木工工作用的不是頭
We learn by body.
而是用身體
How you work is how you remember.
工作能力就是你的記憶
-Keep it up. -Yes.
-加油 -是
-But you are annoying. -What did you say?
-真麻煩 -你說什麼？
-He didn't mean it. -What did he mean then?
-不，他不是這意思 -那是什麼意思？
What's this smell?
這氣味是什麼？
I've never noticed such a strong pheromone.
第一次聞到這種費洛蒙
Shimeji mushrooms?
鴻…鴻喜菇？
There is no space here. Go outside.
別在這種狹窄的地方做啊 搬去外面做
-Bring them outside. -Hurry…
-快點搬出去 -快…
-Take it -You want me to do it?
-拿出去 -我嗎？
What do you think is a manly job?
-你覺得男人的工作是什麼？
Manual labor, of course.
果然還是肉體勞動吧
-Do you like blue-collar workers? -Yes, like truck drivers.
-你喜歡勞動系的啊？ -沒錯，像是卡車司機之類的
You said so because they may be listening to this radio.
根本只是對著現在 聽廣播的觀眾層說的啊
Can't you tell?
被發現了啊？
-You are flattering radio listeners again. -How annoying!
又這麼諂媚了，真令人火大啊
But I like men who work hard without talking.
但我真的很喜歡啊，默默工作的男人
I can't work without talking.
我就無法默默工作啊
But you look nice when you don't talk.
十勝先生偶爾閉嘴應該會很棒
It means I am not working.
那是我沒工作時吧？
That's enough.
夠了啦
It's almost three o'clock.
馬上就要到三點了
Let's call SNACK MAN. Where is he today?
來呼叫點心男吧，他今天在哪裡呢？
It's time for you and I
你和我的時間
Evolutionary theory for you and I
我和你的進化論
Ask Amakusa if you are
有煩惱就問天草
Are you ready, Amakusa?
天草先生？
Worrying about something
去問問天草吧
Hello. I am Junpei Amakusa.
好的，我是天草純平
Here is what I got today.
我收到這樣的煩惱
It's from Kizutsuki, 26 years old, from Saitama.
住在埼玉縣的傷心男孩，26歲
Sometimes I don't know who I am these days.
我最近有時會搞不懂自己是誰
I am working for a top-rated company and I have a girlfriend.
我在一流企業工作，也有女朋友
But I don't feel like myself
但無論是工作還是約會
when I work or when I go out for a date.
總覺得都不是自己
Is this because my current life doesn't fit me well?
這是否代表 現在的生活方式不適合我呢？
So I came to a business district in Tokyo.
所以今天我們來到市區的辦公大樓區
Let me ask people walking by how much they understand themselves.
我想來問問看這裡的人 對自己有多了解
Excuse me. May I ask you something?
能請問一下嗎？
Sure.
是
Who are you?
你是誰呢？
Please answer me without using your name.
請回答我名字以外的答案
Well, I am a businessman.
我想想，我是上班族
Is there a human such as a businessman?
有上班族這種人嗎？
If you quit or your company goes bankrupt, will you also disappear?
若辭去工作或公司消失 你也會從這世界消失嗎？
Then, I am a father and a good husband.
那…我是父親，一個好丈夫
But it's only your family who think of you
但說到父親或好丈夫
as a father and a good husband.
會想起來的除了你的家人之外 也沒其他人了吧
Isn't that good enough?
這樣就夠了吧？
I see. That's one answer.
原來如此，這也算是個答案
Thank you very much. Let me ask another person.
謝謝，我想接著問下一位
Excuse me.
能請問一下嗎？
Are you talking to me?
我嗎？好的
Who are you?
你是誰？
Please answer me without using your name.
請回答我名字以外的答案
I am a dispatch employee and a comedian.
我是派遣公司的契約員工 也是搞笑藝人
Are you a comedian? Can you give me a joke?
你是搞笑藝人嗎？有什麼段子？
Can I show you?
有，我可以表演嗎？
Here you go…
嘿咻…
Is that true?
是這樣嗎？
It wasn't funny. Was it because of your joke or because of you?
好的，剛才出錯的是你 還是你的段子？
It's whether your joke is not funny,
你的段子會這麼無聊
or you are not funny?
是因為你的段子還是你的人？
Which do you think?
你覺得是怎麼樣呢？
As a result, Kizutsuki is a person who knows himself well.
也就是說，從結果來說 傷心男孩應該非常了解自己
It's important to know that you don't know.
不了解是很重要的
He worries whether his current life fits him or not.
適不適合自己的生存方式什麼的
But it depends on how he thinks.
這種事光靠自己的想法就能改變
If you know who you are, you can't change yourself.
反倒是太過了解自己的人
It must be boring.
若是無法改變自己就太無聊了
When you think you don't know who you are,
覺得搞不懂自己時
try to enjoy being yourself.
只要讓自己變得有趣就行了
See you tomorrow.
那麼明天再見吧
If you are worrying about something at snack time…
點心時間的煩惱
Ask Amakusa
就交給天草吧
It's so boring. Why do you like it?
你喜歡聽這種無聊的節目啊？
Do you think it's funny?
你覺得這種有趣嗎？
Amakusa? He is doing well.
天草？他很努力啊
I'm telling you I don't like him.
我的意思是說我不喜歡
What?
什麼？
Doctor.
老師
How is he doing?
他怎麼樣了？
He is doing well.
沒問題的，他有好好做
Inaniwa is taking care of him.
稻庭先生正在幫我看著
How was his physical exam?
他的身體如何？
I'm checking on his cells now.
我正在看他的細胞
The cell structure itself is the same as ours.
細胞構造本身跟我們沒什麼差別
Then…
那麼…
But it doesn't prove anything.
但光是這樣無法證明任何事
I will check his DNA now.
接著我會調查他的遺傳基因
He may have a different type of DNA.
他或許擁有跟我們不同的遺傳基因
It is possible that some kind of power in his DNA
或許是因為這個
has kept him alive and young for 120 years.
他才能保持年輕，活了120年
DNA not only inherits information from our ancestors
遺傳基因不只是祖先 傳承給我們的資訊
but also keeps making our body day by day.
每天都不斷地在打造我們的身體
Normally, only five to 10% of them are working.
一般來說 只用到了百分之五到百分之十的功能
More than 90% are still unknown.
超過百分之九十就是未知領域了
We have countless numbers of effects of DNA
還沒覺醒的遺傳基因功能
that have not awaken yet.
全部潛藏在我們體內
DNA works differently depending on your mental situation.
想法不同，遺傳基因的功能 也會有所不同
That's the theme of my research.
這就是我的研究主題
Someday, people will get over incurable diseases
只要覺得能治癒，總有一天
by believing that they will be cured.
我們也能克服重大病症的
Yes.
是
Thank you.
謝謝您
I really mean it.
這不是在偷懶
I know you are so strange that you wouldn't flatter.
我知道老師是不會偷懶的怪人
Good enough.
好的，這樣就好
Hello, my sister.
是姊姊嗎？
Tsugumi, are you all right?
繼實，你沒事吧？
Don't you have a headache?
頭不痛嗎？
I'm fine. Sorry to have worried you.
我沒事，抱歉讓你擔心了
I was worried about you. You were suffering so much.
我當然會擔心啊，你痛成那樣
I'm fine now.
我已經沒事了
I'm still at the university.
我人在大學
I may come home late today.
今天可能也會晚歸
Again?
什麼？今天也會晚歸嗎？
I'm sorry. Bye.
抱歉，姊姊，先這樣了
Hey, Tsugumi?
等等，繼實？
She is hiding something from me.
她肯定瞞著我些什麼
You are not at the university!
根本就不在大學裡啊
Where are you now?
真是的，跑去哪裡了？
If you know who you are, you can't change yourself.
反倒是太過了解自己的人
It's boring, isn't it?
若是無法改變自己就太無聊了
When you think you don't know who you are,
覺得搞不懂自己時
try to enjoy being yourself.
只要讓自己變得有趣就行了
I'm Tsugaru. May I come in?
我是津輕，可以進去嗎？
Yes.
是
How are you?
打擾了
You worked hard today.
今天辛苦你了
What are you making?
你在做什麼呢？
Your name.
名字
You are the first human I talked to other than my father.
這是我第一次跟父親以外的人談話
I could have seen the world of humans.
這是我第一次看到人類的世界
You are right.
這樣啊
Tsugaru.
而津輕小姐你
You gave me a name.
幫我取了名字
I was so happy.
我非常開心
Is this a name plate?
這是門牌嗎？
I am Ken Fukashi.
我是深志研
Yes. You are Ken Fukashi.
對，你就是深志研
I…
我…
Do you think I can find out who I am other than my name in this place?
今後能在這裡 了解這名字以外的自己嗎？
Do you think I can enjoy being myself?
我能夠讓自己變得有趣嗎？
Do you think I can change myself?
我有辦法改變自己嗎？
Yes.
可以的
You can change yourself.
你一定會改變的
Let's work on it together.
讓我們一起改變吧
Yes.
是
Tsugumi Tsugaru.
津輕繼實小姐
Thank you very much.
謝謝你
Yes.
是
I am glad that I asked for your help.
拜託稻庭學長你，真是太好了
Did you finally find that you are pushing yourself too much?
你總算發現自己在逞強了啊
Don't try to do everything all by yourself.
你不用獨自背負他的事
That man. You are just curious, aren't you?
你不過是出自於探求心吧？
I don't know why I brought him here.
我自己也不明白 不懂為何會帶他下山
I don't know what to do with him.
不知道自己想對他做什麼
Do you think he is an ordinary human,
你真以為他是普通人嗎？
or do you think he is a monster?
還是說，你覺得他真的是怪物？
No.
怎麼可能？
If he is a monster…
如果他真的是怪物…
I will protect you.
我會保護你的
I will keep you safe from a monster.
我會從怪物手中保護你的
I won't let a monster make you suffer.
我不會讓你煩惱的 不會讓怪物造成你的困擾
Inaniwa.
學長
Haruka?
姊姊？
You can't die before I die.
姊姊居然會早一步走 不可能有這種事
Find him.
快把他找來
I need to do more research.
我想多做點調查
As I thought, I was not a human.
我果然不是人類
Please show me who you really are.
請讓我看看你真正的樣子
Please don't come here.
不要過來這裡
THIS DRAMA IS FICTION
（本劇純屬虛構）